The first step of the LoRaWAN Network configuration is the Gateway configuration.
This will allow the Gateway to be aware of the targeted Network Server and also the protocol used.
We saw previously that unfortunately LoRaWAN doesn't specify one protocol between the gateway and the
Network Server.
So, many LoRaWAN players have developed their own solutions.
The protocol used between the Gateway and the Network Server is handled by what we call a packet forwarder.
The most commonly used protocol is UDP SEMTECH packet forwarder, but there are many others like
LoRa Basic Station, also created by Semtech,
LRR created by Actility,
LORIOT packet forwarder uses for LORIOT Network Server and so on.
The problem is that all Network Servers don't support all packet forwarders.
Fortunately, most Gateways support several packet forwarders, so in that case you're pretty sure that
at least one will be compatible with the Network Server.
So, before choosing a Gateway with its packet forwarder, we need to check on the Network Server documentation
the compatibilities they offer. At the time we posted this video, Chirpstack and The Things Stack can both support
Semtech UDP packet forwarder and Basic Station packet forwarder. And in our case, for our private network
configuration, we will use Semtech UDP packet forwarder.
So, everything should work with both Network Servers.